Guide to the Gardiner-Tyler Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Gardiner-Tyler Family Papers
1843-1898
MS 230
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.5
Papers of the Gardiner family of Easthampton, New York and of John Tyler, president of the United States from 1841-1845. The principal figure in the papers is Julia Gardiner Tyler, who married John Tyler in 1844. A number of the letters are exchanges between members of the Tyler family and John Tyler concerning his courtship of Julia Gardiner. Most of the letters were written to Julia Gardiner Tyler and include nearly 200 letters from her eldest son, David, as well as letters from her mother, Juliana McLachlan Gardiner, her sister, Margaret Gardiner Beeckman, and from other of her children. Also in the papers are ca. 650 family letters sent to her mother and sister. The family correspondence discusses social and political life in New York, Washington and Virginia, where Tyler retired with his wife after his presidency. John Tyler is represented only by a small number of letters, mainly on his intended marriage and some fifty-five letters sent to him at the White House on minor matters. Financial and legal documents, printed matter and memorabilia relating to Julia Gardiner Tyler are also in the papers together with a chronicle of Easthampton written by a member of the Gardiner family.
Gardiner family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. J. Randall Creel, 1958; and purchased, 1971.
Arrangement
I. GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE
II. JULIA GARDINER TYLER
III. JULIA McLACHLAN GARDINER
IV. FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
V. MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS
Scope and Contents
Papers of the Gardiner family of Easthampton, New York and of John Tyler, president of the United States from 1841-1845. The principal figure in the papers is Julia Gardiner Tyler, who married John Tyler in 1844. A number of the letters are exchanges between members of the Tyler family and John Tyler concerning his courtship of Julia Gardiner. Most of the letters were written to Julia Gardiner Tyler and include nearly 200 letters from her eldest son, David, as well as letters from her mother, Juliana McLachlan Gardiner, her sister, Margaret Gardiner Beeckman, and from other of her children. Also in the papers are ca. 650 family letters sent to her mother and sister. The family correspondence discusses social and political life in New York, Washington and Virginia, where Tyler retired with his wife after his presidency. John Tyler is represented only by a small number of letters, mainly on his intended marriage and some fifty-five letters sent to him at the White House on minor matters. Financial and legal documents, printed matter and memorabilia relating to Julia Gardiner Tyler are also in the papers together with a chronicle of Easthampton written by a member of the Gardiner family.
Biographical / Historical
For charts outlining the genealogical relations of the Gardiner and Tyler families, please consult the Genealogical Charts.
Families; Presidents' spouses -- United States; Wives; East Hampton (N.Y.) -- History; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; New York (State); Southern States; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- Politics and government -- 19th century; Virginia -- Social life and customs; Washington (D.C.) -- Social life and customs; Account books; Beeckman, Margaret Gardiner, 1822-1857; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868; Evarts, William Maxwell, 1818-1901; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874; Gardiner, Alexander, 1818-1851; Gardiner, David Lyon, 1816-1892; Gardiner, David, 1784-1844; Gardiner, Juliana McLachlan, 1799-1864; Horsford, Phoebe Gardiner; Mathewson, A. J.; Semple, John A.; Taylor, Tazewell; Tyler, D. Gardiner (David Gardiner), 1846-1927; Tyler, John, 1790-1862; Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1820-1889; Gardner family; Tyler family
- Correspondence, Series I
  - 1805-1842 August (Box 1, Folder 1-28)
  - 1842 September - 1845 January 18 (Box 2, Folder 29-62)
  - 1845 January 19 - 1848 December 28 (Box 3, Folder 63-107)
  - 1849 January - 1855 (Box 4, Folder 108-143)
  - 1856-1898, undated (Box 5, Folder 144-177)
- JULIA GARDINER TYLER, Series II
  - Family correspondence
    - Beeckman, Henry Gardiner, 1852-1874, undated (Box 6, Folder 178-179)
    - Beeckman, Gilbert and Madeleine, 1865, 1875 (Box 6, Folder 180)
    - Beeckman, Margaret, 1837-1854 (Box 6, Folder 181-188)
    - Dayton, Daniel, 1865, 1867 (Box 6, Folder 189)
    - Denison, Alice Tyler, 1844-1845 (Box 6, Folder 190)
    - Ellis, Pear Tyler, 1872, 1874-1876 (Box 6, Folder 191)
    - Gardiner, Alexander, 1836-1850 (Box 6, Folder 192-193)
    - Gardiner, David, undated (Box 6, Folder 194)
    - Gardiner, David Lyon, 1844-1846 (Box 6, Folder 195)
    - Gardiner, Juliana, 1835-1863 (Box 7, Folder 196-199)
    - Gardiner, Nathaniel, 1844 (Box 7, Folder 200)
    - Gardiner, Mary, 1839-1878, undated (Box 7, Folder 201)
    - Gardiner, Samuel Buell, 1865-1876 (Box 7, Folder 202)
    - Gardiner, William H., 1845 (Box 7, Folder 203)
    - Hartshorn, E. G., 1870-1879 (Box 7, Folder 204)
    - Harsford, E. N., Mamie and Lillian, 1869-1878 (Box 7, Folder 205)
    - Harsford, Phoebe Gardiner, 1844-1880, undated (Box 7, Folder 206-207)
    - Rockwell, M. D., 1874-1882 (Box 7, Folder 208)
    - Semple, James A., 1863-1880 (Box 7, Folder 209-211)
    - Semple, Letitia Tyler, 1867 (Box 7, Folder 212)
    - Spencer, Julia G., 1865-1871, undated (Box 7, Folder 213-214)
    - Spencer, William H., 1868-1880, undated (Box 7, Folder 215-216)
    - Tyler, David Gardiner, 1863-1881, undated (Box 8, Folder 217-223)
    - Tyler, John Jr., 1878 (Box 8, Folder 224)
    - Tyler, John Alexander, 1864-1882 (Box 8, Folder 225-227)
    - Tyler, John C., 1864-1868 (Box 8, Folder 228)
    - Tyler, Lachlan, 1862-1882, undated (Box 8, Folder 229-231)
    - Tyler, Lyon Gardiner, 1874, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 232)
    - "The President and Mrs. Robert Tyler,", 1843 (Box 8, Folder 233)
    - Tyler, Sarah Griswold, 1867-1879 (Box 8, Folder 234)
    - Tyler, Nannie Bridges, 1868, 1871 (Box 8, Folder 235)
    - Tyler, Robert Fitzwalter, 1877-1885 (Box 8, Folder 236)
    - Tyler, William, 1866 (Box 8, Folder 237)
    - Waller, Elizabeth Tyler, 1844-1845 (Box 8, Folder 238)
    - Wells, Annie, 1871-1877 (Box 8, Folder 239)
    - Miscellaneous, 1837-1880, undated (Box 8, Folder 240-241)
  - General correspondence
    - A, 1843-1876 (Box 9, Folder 242)
    - Atwood, Anna Montgomery, 1862-1868, undated (Box 9, Folder 243)
    - B, 1843-1880 (Box 9, Folder 244-245)
    - Butler, Benjamin F., 1864-1865 (Box 9, Folder 246)
    - C, 1831-1882 (Box 9, Folder 247-248)
    - Cameron, William E., 1882 (Box 9, Folder 249)
    - Chalmevs, Belle C., 1869-1882 (Box 9, Folder 250)
    - Christian, Judge John B., undated (Box 9, Folder 251)
    - Clopton, William H. and Maria G., 1859-1871 (Box 9, Folder 252)
    - Conger, Mary, 1843-1869 (Box 9, Folder 253)
    - D, 1844-1870 (Box 9, Folder 254)
    - E, 1844-1876 (Box 9, Folder 255)
    - Evarts, William M., 1866-1886 (Box 9, Folder 256-259)
    - Evarts, Southmayd and Choate, 1867-1876 (Box 9, Folder 260)
    - F, 1853-1876 (Box 9, Folder 261)
    - G, 1844-1877 (Box 10, Folder 262)
    - Gayle, Capt. Robert H., 1864-1865 (Box 10, Folder 263)
    - H, 1864-1874 (Box 10, Folder 264-265)
    - Healy, Rev. Father Patrick F., 1872-1878 (Box 10, Folder 266)
    - Ives, Cora S., 1874-1875 (Box 10, Folder 267)
    - J, 1864-1877 (Box 10, Folder 268)
    - Joannes, George the Count, 1869 (Box 10, Folder 269)
    - K, 1865-1875 (Box 10, Folder 270)
    - L, 1848-1875 (Box 10, Folder 271)
    - Loretto, Sister, 1872-1876 (Box 10, Folder 272)
    - Lyons, James and Mrs., 1868-1878 (Box 10, Folder 273-275)
    - M, 1865-1882 (Box 10, Folder 276-277)
    - Mathewson, A. J., 1869-1877 (Box 10, Folder 278)
    - McLean, John, 1843 (Box 10, Folder 279)
    - Mulford, Brig. Gen. John E., undated (Box 10, Folder 280)
    - N, 1875 (Box 10, Folder 281)
    - O, 1865, 1876 (Box 10, Folder 282)
    - P, 1857-1878 (Box 10, Folder 283)
    - Pierrepont, Edward, 1869 (Box 10, Folder 284)
    - R, 1844-1878 (Box 10, Folder 285)
    - S, 1843-1879 (Box 11, Folder 286-287)
    - T, 1865-1880 (Box 11, Folder 288)
    - Taylor, Tazewell, 1865-1868 (Box 11, Folder 289)
    - V, 1864-1872 (Box 11, Folder 290)
    - W, 1854-1875 (Box 11, Folder 291-292)
    - Walker, Maj. and Mrs. Norman T., 1863-1867 (Box 11, Folder 293)
    - X - Z, 1871, 1873, undated (Box 11, Folder 294)
    - Unidentified, 1837-1881,undated (Box 11, Folder 295-298)
  - Outgoing correspondence
    - A - E, 1863-1880 (Box 11, Folder 299)
    - F - L, 1863-1875 (Box 11, Folder 300)
    - M - Z, 1843-1870 (Box 11, Folder 301)
    - "My Dear Brother,", 1844-1850 (Box 11, Folder 302)
    - "My Dear Sons,", 1866-1888 (Box 11, Folder 303)
    - Unidentified, 1854-1880 (Box 11, Folder 304)
  - Bills and receipts, 1821-1882, undated (Box 12, Folder 305-320)
- JULIA McLACHLAN GARDINER, Series III
  - General
    - A - Z, 1833-1864 (Box 13, Folder 321-322)
    - Outgoing, 1845-1865 (Box 13, Folder 323)
  - Personal
    - Gardiner, Alexander, 1846-1850 (Box 13, Folder 324)
    - Beeckman, Margaret, 1844-1857 (Box 13, Folder 325-328)
    - Gardiner, David Lyon, 1834-1867 (Box 13, Folder 329)
    - Tyler, David and John, 1857, 1859 (Box 13, Folder 330)
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1835-1864 (Box 13, Folder 331-338)
  - Bills and receipts, 1852-1864 (Box 13, Folder 339-341)
- FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE, Series IV
  - Beeckman, Henry Gardiner
    - Tyler, David Gardiner et alii., 1860-1869 (Box 14, Folder 342)
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1865, 1871 (Box 14, Folder 343)
    - General correspondence, 1863-1875 (Box 14, Folder 344)
  - Beeckman, Margaret Gardiner
    - Beeckman, Catherine Livingston, 1849-1853 (Box 14, Folder 345)
    - Beeckman, Gilbert L., 1848-1857 (Box 14, Folder 346)
    - Beeckman, John H., 1848-1850 (Box 14, Folder 347)
    - Gardiner, Alexander, 1846-1847 (Box 14, Folder 348)
    - Gardiner, David Lyon, 1851-1855 (Box 14, Folder 349)
    - Gardiner, Juliana M., 1844-1854 (Box 14, Folder 350)
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1844-1857 (Box 14, Folder 351-354)
    - A - Z, 1847-1854 (Box 14, Folder 355)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1843-1855 (Box 14, Folder 356-357)
    - Bills and receipts, 1848-1853 (Box 14, Folder 358)
  - Gardiner, Alexander
    - Gardiner, Juliana, 1845-1851 (Box 14, Folder 359)
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1844-1849 (Box 14, Folder 360)
    - Beeckman, Margaret Gardiner, 1844-1846 (Box 14, Folder 361)
    - Gardiner, David L., 1845-1847 (Box 14, Folder 362)
    - General correspondence, 1846-1850 (Box 14, Folder 363)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1845-1850 (Box 14, Folder 364)
      Scope and Contents
      Also includes a letter to an unidentified Judge from "Alexander," 1864 September 2.
  - Gardiner, David
    - A - Z, 1832-1834 (Box 14, Folder 365-366)
  - Gardiner, David Lyon
    - Gardiner, Juliana, 1854-1858 (Box 14, Folder 367)
    - Gardiner, Alexander, 1844-1850 (Box 14, Folder 368)
    - Horsford, E. N., 1859, 1861 (Box 14, Folder 369)
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1845-1868 (Box 14, Folder 370)
    - Financial papers, 1852-1858 (Box 14, Folder 371)
  - Spencer, Julia Tyler
    - General, 1865-1870 (Box 15, Folder 372)
    - Outgoing, 1864-1869 (Box 15, Folder 373)
    - Tyler, David Gardiner et alii., 1865-1870 (Box 15, Folder 374)
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1866-1871 (Box 15, Folder 375)
    - Tyler, Julia G. and William H. Spencer, 1876-1882 (Box 15, Folder 376)
  - Tyler, David Gardiner
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1866-1886 (Box 15, Folder 377)
    - Tyler, John Alexander et alii., 1864-1880 (Box 15, Folder 378)
    - General correspondence, 1869-1877 (Box 15, Folder 379)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1871, 1874 (Box 15, Folder 380)
  - Tyler, John
    - A - Z, 1844-1868 (Box 15, Folder 381-382)
    - Notes, 1844-1854 (Box 15, Folder 383)
  - Tyler, John Alexander
    - Semple, James A., 1866-06-01 (Box 15, Folder 383a)
    - Tyler, David Gardiner, 1864-1865 (Box 15, Folder 384)
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1872 (Box 15, Folder 385)
  - Tyler, Lachlan
    - Tyler, David Gardiner, 1867-1869 (Box 15, Folder 386)
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1881 (Box 15, Folder 387)
    - General correspondence, 1875-1881 (Box 15, Folder 388)
  - Tyler, Letitia Christian
    - Semple, Letitia Tyler, 1837 (Box 15, Folder 389)
  - Tyler, Lyon Gardiner
    - Tyler, David Gardiner et alii., 1869-1871 (Box 15, Folder 390)
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1870-1874 (Box 15, Folder 391)
    - General correspondence, 1876-1882 (Box 15, Folder 392)
  - Tyler, Pearl
    - Tyler, David Gardiner et alii., 1866-1881 (Box 15, Folder 393)
    - Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1873, 1881 (Box 15, Folder 394)
    - General correspondence, 1870-1881 (Box 15, Folder 395)
  - Tyler, Robert Fitzwalter
    - Semple, James A., 1878 (Box 15, Folder 396)
  - Others, 1848-1873 (Box 15, Folder 397)
- MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS, Series V
  - Gardiner family
    - Deeds, undated (Box 16, Folder 398-400)
      - Oversized deeds, 1784, 1817-1818, 1848, 1878 (Box 19)
    - Legal papers (Box 16, Folder 401-402)
  - Gardiner, Alexander, 1847
    - Certificates of appointment as Commissioner to take deeds, depositions, and deeds in Ohio and Louisiana, 1847 (Box 19)
  - Gardiner, David
    - Account books, 1830-1851 (Box 16, Folder 403)
      - Oversized accounting sheet, 1817-1821 (Box 19)
  - Tyler, Julia Gardiner
    - Cancelled checks, 1854-1874 (Box 16, Folder 404-406)
    - Legal papers, 1865-1867 (Box 16, Folder 407)
  - Tyler, Lyon Gardiner
    - Absentee record, University of Virgina, 1873-1874 (Box 16, Folder 408)
  - Beeckman, H. G.
    - Grades, Washington (Va.) College, 1868-1869 (Box 16, Folder 409)
    - Invitations and calling cards, 1844-1874 (Box 16, Folder 410-411)
    - Envelopes (Box 16, Folder 412)
    - Indentures (Box 17, Folder 413)
  - Legal papers, 1850-1869 (Box 17, Folder 414)
  - Manuscripts
    - 1845-1865 (Box 17, Folder 415)
    - "Chronicles of Easthampton,", undated (Box 17, Folder 416-418)
    - undated (Box 17, Folder 419-425)
    - Notes, undated (Box 18, Folder 426)
    - Printed material, undated (Box 18, Folder 427-428)